[ ominous , pulsing music ]
[ drone whirring ]
[ birds calling ]
[ Gabi ] Imagine , there was a time when the whole world looked like this .
[ Winston scoffs ] Imagine there was another paddle ...
And long after we 're gone , this thing will still be here .
It 'd better be , it cost enough . Hey ...
Pass me a sandwich .
- What 's on it ? - Roast beef ...
- Monster . - And mustard . Fucking Dijon , baby !
[ scoffs ] " Baby " ?
Where did you get Dijon anyway ?
Oh , I know a guy who might know a guy who knows another guy who basically ...
knows me .
- [ ominous music ] - [ trees creaking ]
[ bugs chirring ]
- [ crack ] - [ electronic feedback ]
- Shit ! - What ?
For fuck 's sakes , Gabi . How far out ?
About two k 's , but there was a guy .
- I 'll go get it . - No , we 've still got four more cameras to check .
Just drop me . I 'll meet you in the next valley .
- People disappear in this forest . - Come on , Winston .
They were crusty old hippies . They probably just moved on to their next squat .
Sometimes you 're just like those whiteys .
" Danger ! " " Where ? Oh , let me go see . "
We can 't just leave our trash here .
[ sighs ]
One hour .
- [ footstep ] - [ soft growling ]
[ distant growl ]
[ wind blowing , trees creaking ]
[ soft , ominous music ]
[ water gurgling ]
[ trees creaking ]
[ soft , ethereal music ]
[ plastic rustling ]
[ rustling continues ]
[ sighs ]
Winston , come in . Over .
[ static on radio ]
Winston , come in .
[ radio beeps ]
[ guttural growling ]
- [ guttural squeal ] - [ gasps ]
[ suspenseful music ]
[ guttural growls continue ]
[ high-pitched squealing ]
- [ squelch ] - [ screams ]
Oh fuck !
[ whimpers ]
[ groaning ]
[ soft squeal ]
[ crying softly ]
Winston ... I need help .
- [ guttural squeal ] - [ leaves rustling ]
[ labored breathing ]
[ grunting , screaming ]
[ distant screaming ]
Fuck .
[ fast-paced , suspenseful music ]
Shit !
Gabi , copy . Over .
Fuck .
[ screaming ]
[ whimpering ]
Gabi !
[ shuddering breath ]
[ Winston ] Gabi !
[ trees creaking ]
Gabi ?
Gabs ?
[ trees creaking ]
[ soft , ominous music ]
- [ distant screech ] - Oh !
Come on !
[ growling , snarling ]
Gabs ?
[ frustrated grunt ]
[ trees creaking ]
[ frogs croaking , chirping ]
Hello ?
[ strains ]
[ whimpers ]
Fuck .
[ panting ]
[ growling , snapping ]
[ growling continues ]
[ screeching , squealing ]
[ coughing ]
[ spits ]
[ soft squelching ]
[ distant screeching ]
[ Barend ] Hurry .
- I 'm sorry , I 'm sorry ... - Shh ... Who sent you ?
My name is Gabi Pekeur . Please ... Please , they 're looking for me .
You broke our trap .
[ softly ] It 's okay ...
[ wry chuckle ]
[ sighs ]
[ creature growling softly ]
- [ creature snarling ] - What the fuck ?
[ soft , dramatic music ]
Who are you ?
Barend .
You from the city ?
Forestry Station .
How many of you out there now ?
Two .
[ cutting ]
[ distant growling ]
Elephant ?
Just the one old cow .
What 's your name ?
[ Barend ] Stefan .
He doesn 't speak much .
Bring me the livers .
[ fat sizzling ]
Mother of Creation and Destruction , you are the Earth and we are your children .
Porcini ...
Costs a fortune in your fancy restaurants .
[ creatures growling , snarling ]
[ snarling , shrieking ]
[ cloth ripping ]
- [ rasping squeal ] - [ footsteps approaching ]
[ squealing ]
[ Gabi blows ]
I saw something out there .
Someone .
There was something wrong with his face .
[ sniffs ]
[ soft squelching ]
[ birds chirping ]
[ water splashing ]
[ footsteps receding ]
[ gentle , ominous music ]
[ whimpers ]
[ gasps ]
- [ Gabi ] Winston , come in . - [ static on radio ]
Winston , come in .
Where are you ? Are you okay ?
Over .
Asshole .
[ Winston on radio ] Gabi ...
Winston ? Where are you ?
I 'm ...
- Winston ! - What is this ?
- [ creatures squealing ] - [ Winston screaming ]
Winston , what ?
[ static ]
[ bushpig grunting ]
[ bushpig squealing ]
[ Barend strains ]
Mother , we ask your forgiveness .
We join your servant in traveling to your bosom .
[ crying softly ]
[ Stefan sniffing ]
[ plank rattling ]
[ soft , ethereal music ]
[ Barend ] Hey !
- We don 't make fire in daylight . - They 're looking for me .
[ scoffs ]
- They would 've been here already . - I heard him , over the radio .
[ sighs ]
I 'll take you tomorrow .
What ?
Winston , are you there ?
[ static on radio ]
Is anybody there ?
He 's intelligent .
- He should be learning . - He is learning .
Where 's his mother ?
Bone cancer . Thirteen years now .
I 'm sorry .
Collateral damage .
And what did you use to do ?
I was a scientist , plant pathology .
But after Lily ...
You don 't have to .
Lily was a chemical engineer .
At first she said her blood ... was hurting .
Later it was like she was being eaten up from the inside .
Benzene .
When the doctors gave up ,
Lily wanted to come back here , where we spent our honeymoon .
Where he was conceived .
And then ?
Then I met her .
Who ?
God .
[ soft , ominous music ]
Thank you .
Something to remember us by .
[ soft squelching ]
- [ door bangs shut ] - [ gasps ]
Shh ...
[ creatures growling outside ]
[ squealing outside ]
[ whimpering ]
- [ bang on door ] - [ Gabi whimpers ]
- Are you going to keep quiet ? - Mm ...
- [ bang on door ] - [ screeching call ]
[ banging on walls , roof ]
[ growling ]
If they get in , stay against the wall ... They 're blind .
Who ?
- [ banging on door ] - [ screeching , growling continues ]
[ banging on door ]
[ soft squelching ]
[ dramatic music ]
[ screams ]
[ creature shrieks , growls ]
[ growling ]
[ knife clatters on floor ]
[ soft growling ]
[ screeching ]
[ whimpers ]
[ growling ]
- [ Gabi strains ] - [ creature shrieking ]
[ rattling growl ]
[ shrieking recedes ]
What the fuck ?
Let him .
Get the blood off her .
[ Gabi crying softly ]
[ retches ]
Bring the blood . Burn the rest .
It 's a fungus .
Seems to prefer Homo sapiens .
It feeds on the eyes , the mouth , the lungs .
First it grows down , saves the muscles for later , connects to the fungal network ,
filling up with spores until it 's ready to ...
repeat itself .
And so ...
finally , the apes return to the trees .
What in God 's name are you talking about ?
The largest organism on the planet lives right here , underneath us .
Older than human history , it 's been growing ...
waiting , ripening .
And it 's ready to spread .
And that is your god ?
She was here long before the apes started dreaming of gods .
- Do you believe that ? - Bedtime .
[ chirring , distant animal calls ]
[ soft , ominous music ]
[ soft squelching ]
[ gasps ]
Pretty .
[ birds chirping ]
[ camera shutter clicks ]
[ gentle music ]
[ Stefan chuckles softly ]
[ scared exhale ]
- Monster . - What ?
- Monster ! - Keep your devilish devices away from us !
Apparitions ! Abominations !
Out ! Go !
[ soft , ominous music ]
[ Barend ] To see the future of humanity , observe monkeys in captivity .
Aggressive hoarding of limited resources ,
asserting hierarchies through sexual violence .
Every day , the human habitat resembles more closely a cage .
- [ tree creaking ] - [ ominous music building ]
[ creaking continues ]
[ soft squelching ]
[ scoffs ]
[ disgusted sigh ]
Time to go .
[ door slams shut ]
- Dad ! - No !
[ items clattering ]
[ Gabi ] Hey ...
It 's okay .
I could always come visit you .
Let me take him with me . Please .
[ scoffs ]
So if this thing is under the forest , why do you live here ?
Why aren 't you guys infected ?
- Hey ! - But we are .
Hey ! Barend ?
This is his .
[ torch clicks on ]
This belongs to my boss .
Wait ...
That 's where they live !
[ suspenseful music ]
This is madness .
[ crying softly ]
- [ Winston gasps ] - [ whimpers ]
[ strained breathing ]
[ low growl ]
Gabi ?
Please ...
Kill ... me .
No . [ sniffs ] I can get you to the hospital .
[ straining ]
No !
You want him to become one of them ?
We can help him .
[ sobbing ]
[ creatures growling , squealing ]
Come .
[ growling continues ]
[ creatures squealing ]
[ Barend ] Stefan !
[ door shuts ]
[ shuddering breath ]
[ bugs chirring ]
[ whimpers ]
[ coughing , sniffing ]
I know you have medicine .
Please .
[ footsteps receding ]
[ door opens , closes ]
Where did your dad go ?
To pray .
And your mother ?
She called me her little monkey .
She must 've loved you very much .
Loved ...
Love ...
Loved .
She lives in the forest .
What ?
She lives in the forest now ...
My mother .
[ soft , ominous music ]
I 'll show you .
[ tree creaking ]
[ creaking intensifies ]
No ...
You know there 's a whole world out there , right ?
You could learn to read , to write ...
You could work with me .
You could become a game ranger , work with animals .
Anything you like .
Drive a truck .
Drink beer .
And there are girls .
That 's a pity .
Dad says they 're all gonna die .
[ soft , dramatic music ]
[ trees creaking ]
[ whimpering ]
[ straining ]
Eat it !
Are you ready ?
I 'm staying .
[ birds chirping ]
There she is .
[ gentle creaking ]
[ eerie music ]
[ Gabi and Stefan chuckling ]
[ Barend writing ]
We also started writing a manifesto once .
But we were ... high .
And we weren 't very clever .
Not as clever as you .
Nature is scripture .
" For the invisible things of him from the creation of the world
are clearly seen , being understood by the things that are made . "
I think we 're a bit beyond that .
[ scoffs ]
Are we ?
You don 't believe me , but you believe in a central nervous system
which promises you that it 's the only intelligence on Earth ?
Three hundred years ago we started the Industrial Revolution .
Nothing less than a declaration of war .
And she 's losing .
So you 're saying this is intentional ?
[ scoffs ] That 's the difference between science and ...
Madness ?
Faith .
Seeing is believing .
[ soft chuckle ]
" If ye had faith as a grain of mustard seed ,
ye might say unto this sycamine tree ,
Be thou plucked up by the root , and be thou planted in the sea . "
[ dramatic music building ]
How will you ever convince anyone ...
I don 't need to convince anyone !
I want to understand .
[ chuckling ]
" Understand " ?
Look at your world ...
The creatures are crawling in their cages of shit ,
clinging to dream worlds on silicon screens .
You swarm ... like maggots around your neon towers
and multiply exponentially in the glow of the whores and false goddesses
dancing on the walls of the neon towers in the fire of infinite explosions !
All you know is excess and devouring and more , and more , and more !
Faster and faster over the abyss and into the very fires of hell
where the smoke and brimstone will spew forth from your mouths ...
Look ...
Look how you congratulate yourselves on your achievements ,
your tremendous victories ...
The internal combustion engine , the nuclear bomb ...
Democracy .
The willing surrender of the highest decision-making power to every zygote
who won the grand victory of fertilization . And look ... Look where that got you .
Look at humanity choosing its own demise time and time again !
Hurrah for your free will ! Hurrah !
A band of apes climbing up the burning mountain
to escape the floodwaters that want to engulf them !
A swarm of locusts swirling around the Earth ,
faster and faster until the atmosphere goes up in a ring of fire !
And you think you can save them ?
No ...
No , no , no .
" In those days , men will seek death but will not find it ,
they will long to die but death will elude them . "
If you love them so much ...
rather wish for mercy , a swift end to the Anthropocene .
Show me .
[ trees creaking ]
[ Barend blows ]
[ ethereal music ]
[ creaking ]
[ exhales ]
[ leaves rustling ]
[ water gurgling ]
[ breathing intensifies ]
[ soft squelching ]
[ squelching intensifies ]
[ gentle creaking ]
[ gills vibrating ]
[ dull thudding ]
[ rattling growl ]
Where was I ?
In the dreamtime .
How long was I out for ?
Fifteen minutes , maybe .
It felt like days .
What did she tell you ?
[ gasps ]
You heard her .
You know what she wants .
[ tree creaking ]
No .
[ gills vibrating ]
But he 's innocent .
[ creaking intensifies ]
I begged ...
I implored ...
[ birds chirping ]
[ Gabi laughing ]
[ talking indistinctly ]
We must get away from here .
[ dramatic music ]
[ Barend gasps ]
[ door opens , closes ]
Hey , come on . We have to go .
[ soft , suspenseful music ]
Son ?
What are you doing ?
Haven 't I always protected you ?
What are you waiting for , hm ?
It all ends the same way .
Do you know where she 's taking you ?
- She 's going to sell you as a slave . - He 's lying .
They 'll work you till the flesh falls from your bones , and then they 'll eat you .
That 's what they do .
Let 's go , Stefan .
- Long enough to taste joy . - Mm ... It 's all about sex for your kind .
Vermin children surviving on the scraps of a decaying world .
Is that what you told him , huh ?
What you wrote in your manifesto ?
- Please , that 's my life . - I 'll tell the whole world about you !
She 'll never let you leave .
Stefan ?
There 's nothing out there for you , son .
Stefan ...
Please .
Abandon me now , and your mother died for nothing .
- You murdered her . - She came here to die !
Remember our big journey , Stefan .
Our pilgrimage .
It 's time . All of us , very soon , into the world .
[ ominous music ]
- Where are we going , Dad ? - To make a sacrifice .
[ music intensifies ]
But we haven 't brought anything , Dad .
[ leaves rustling ]
God will provide .
[ creature growling , snapping ]
[ rasping screech ]
She has chosen you , my son .
Your body ... our message .
[ tense , ominous music ]
It 's time for your pilgrimage .
[ creature snarling ]
Because I love the world so much ...
[ groans ]
Dad ?
[ soft squelching ]
[ creature squealing ]
- [ Gabi panting ] - [ creature growling ]
[ creature shrieking ]
[ both straining ]
We must ...
We must obey her .
[ tree creaking ]
Please , Dad ...
Stefan !
- [ Gabi straining ] - [ tree roots creaking ]
[ Barend crying softly ]
I knew you would not forsake me .
[ straining ]
You 've been sent .
[ grunts ]
- [ bow clattering ] - [ gasps , grunts ]
[ Gabi screams ]
No , Dad !
[ Barend , Gabi grunting ]
[ screeching snarl ]
[ Stefan screaming ]
- [ straining ] - [ knife slicing ]
" And thy seed shall possess the gate of his enemies . "
We have to obey her !
[ creature snarling ]
[ squelch ]
[ labored breathing ]
[ axe drops ]
It was just a test , son .
I would never ...
[ creature snarling ]
We must believe .
Do it !
[ Barend whimpering ]
Come on .
[ tree creaking ]
[ sobbing softly ]
[ soft squelching ]
[ gasps ]
[ birds chirping ]
[ Barend ] The human race is standing on the first of many tipping points ...
- [ whimpers ] - [ sombre music ]
... unwilling to change , and ready to destroy itself .
[ coughs ]
All it needs is a nudge .
[ straining ]
[ labored breathing ]
Please ...
We 're about to witness the greatest reckoning of all time .
[ sobbing ]
[ birds chirping ]
Leave me here .
Go out ...
into the world .
[ shallow labored breathing ]
Show me mercy ...
Please .
I beg you .
[ soft , dramatic music ]
- [ wind blowing ] - [ leaves rustling ]
[ distant screeching ]
Love ...
Loved .
[ traffic bustling ]
[ sirens wailing ]
[ car honking ]
[ indistinct chatter ]
[ soft squelching ]
[ dramatic music ]